Finding Aid for the Edward Norton Barnhart papers, 1890, 1895, 1940-1954
UCLA Library Special Collections
Edward Norton Barnhart papers
1890, 1895, 1940-1954
2010
Barnhart, Edward Norton, 1909- 1988
6 boxes (3 linear ft.)
Edward Norton Barnhart was a professor of Rhetoric at the University of California, Berkeley and also served as bibliographer for the Japanese American Evacuation and Resettlement Collection there. This collection consists of copies and originals of reports, research papers, and publications related to the Japanese American Evacuation and Resettlement Collection Study and includes War Relocation Authority (WRA) publications and statistical reports on evacuation and resettlement. The collection also includes correspondence of the Tajiris, mostly regarding the preparation of a pamphlet on the Japanese American war efforts, as well as a small collection of personal records of Peruvian Japanese and their families interned at Santa Fe and Crystal City from the law offices of Wayne M. Collins. Materials in this collection are primarily in English with some in Japanese.
University of California, Los Angeles. Library Special Collections. Los Angeles, California 90095-1575
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. STORED OFF-SITE AT SRLF. Advance notice is required for access to the collection. Please contact UCLA Library Special Collections for paging information.
Biography
Edward Norton Barnhart (1909-1988), Professor Emeritus of Rhetoric at the University of California, Berkeley, served as bibliographer for the university's Japanese American Evacuation and Resettlement Study (JERS) collection. The JERS project received the Woodrow Wilson Award of the American Political Science Association for the most distinguished work in political science published in 1954. As the bibliographer, he was responsible for creating an inventory for the collection.
Barnhart began his scholarly career in the field of psychology, but after joining the government services as a Public Opinion Analyst in the Office of Facts and Figures (later known as the Office of War Information), he started focusing on issues in communication and public policy. In particular, he was interested in examining the legal implications of government bowing down to public opinion pressures during wartime. Such research was embodied in a book he wrote with two others, titled Prejudice, War and the Constituion (1954), which stems from JERS, and deals with the political characteristics and constitutional significance of the wartime internment of Japanese Americans. He also wrote articles on Peruvian Japanese internees in the United States.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of various materials related to the Japanese American Evacuation and Resettlement Study (JERS) collection at the University of California, Berkeley, such as statistical reports, newsletters, and research papers. A large portion of the collection comprises of War Relocation Authority (WRA) documents and publications from relocation centers. Also included in the collection are approximately 100 letters addressed to and from Larry Tajiri, editor of the Pacific Citizen newspaper, and his wife. Content of these correspondences mainly regard the the preparation of a new pamphlet to be printed by the Japanese American Citizen's League (JACL) on the Japanese American war efforts. In addition, the collection contains photocopied office files of Wayne M. Collins, a civil rights attorney with the American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU) who served as legal counsel for the Peruvian Japanese interned in the United States during World War II, and thus a handful of personal records of Peruvian Japanese and their families interned at Santa Fe and Crystal City. Materials in this collection are primarily in English with some in Japanese.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Preliminary inventory
WRA statistical reports
Copies of reports, publication excerpts, research papers, and bibliographies
WRA reports, newsletters, and summary reports
Camp newsletters
Correspondence of the Tajiris (Mr. and Mrs. Larry Tajiri)
Copies of reports, publications, and a research paper
Office files (photocopies) of Wayne M. Collins
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Barnhart, Edward Norton, 1909- --Archives.; Japanese American Research Project (University of California, Los Angeles).; Bibliographers--United States--Archival resources.; Japanese Americans--Evacuation and relocation, 1942-1945.
Other Index Terms Related to this Collection
Collins, Wayne M.
Related Material
Japanese American Research Project Collection of Material about Japanese in the United States (Collection 2010). Available at Library Special Collections, UCLA.
Container List
The Edward Norton Barnhart papers are found in Boxes 46-51 of the Japanese American Research Project Collection of Material about Japanese in the United States (Collection 2010).
- 1. Preliminary inventory, undated
  The inventory lists the items found within the Japanese American Evacuation and Resettlement Study (JERS) collection, University of California, Berkeley.
  - Inventory list of the Japanese American Evacuation and Resettlement Study (JERS) collection, undated (Box 46, Folder 1)
- 2. WRA statistical reports, 1943-1946
  Reports relate to the evacuation and resettlement from the War Relocation Authority (WRA) Relocation Planning Division, Statistical Section.
  - Reports on weekly leaves and net absences on leave by centers, 1943 June 19-1946 March 23 (Box 46, Folder 2)
    Includes: Weekly Leaves by Centers, weekly report, no. 5-33; Net Absences on Leave by Centers, weekly report, no. 34-133; and Net Absences on Leave, Tule Lake.
  - Reports on seasonal leaves from centers, 1943 December 25-1944 May 31 (Box 46, Folder 3)
    Includes: Seasonal Leaves, Departures by Center, State and County of Destination, Weekly Report, no. 31-45; Seasonal Leave by Centers, Weekly Report, County of Destination, no. 1-30; and Seasonal Leaves, Departures by Center, State and County of Destination, Monthly Report, no. 46-47
  - Reports on indefinite leaves from centers, 1943 May 1-1945 December 1 (Box 46, Folder 4)
    Includes: General Indefinite Leaves by Centers, Dependents and Workers, semi-monthly report, no. 1-18; Indefinite Leave by Areas, Number of Evacuees on Indefinite Leave Who Have Reported Departures, Arrival or Change of Address by Relocation Areas, States and Important Cities, semi-monthly report, no. 1-38; Indefinite Leaves by Centers, Weekly Report, State of Destination, no. 1-24a; Indefinite Leaves, State of Destination, weekly report, no. 25-30; Indefiniteand Indefinite Leaves by Area, weekly report, no. 16; Indefinite Leaves, Departures by Center, State of Destination, Weekly Report, no. 31-45; Indefinite Leaves, Departures by Center, State of Destination, Monthly Report, no. 46-47; and Indefinite Leave Departures, State of First Destination by Type of Leave, monthly report, no. 2-4
  - Reported Relocation by States, monthly report, no. 1-12, 1945 February 1-1946 January 1 (Box 46, Folder 5)
  - Returns to West Coast, City, Cumulative, monthly report, no. 1-12; and Returns to West Coast, County and Citizenship, Cumulative, monthly report, no. 1-12, 1945 June 30-1946 March 31 (Box 46, Folder 6)
  - Terminal Departures from Centers, State of First Destination by Center, weekly report, no. 1-48; and Terminal Departures from Centers, Cumulative Summary, State of First Destination by Centers, monthly report, no. 1-12, 1945 January 6-December 1; and 1945 December 31-1946 March 30 (Box 46, Folder 7)
  - Selective Service and Volunteers, Weekly Report, no. 10-52, 1944 November 4-1945 November 30 (Box 46, Folder 8)
  - Reported Casualties Among Soldiers of Japanese Descent, by State, County, and City of Pre-Evacuation Address. With Supplements, no. 1-10, 1944 December 16, and 1944 December 17-1945 November 30 (Box 46, Folder 9)
    For the States of California, Oregon, Washington and Arizona, and Territories of Alaska and Hawaii
  - Cumulative Casualties by Center (Reported Casualties Among Soldiers of Japanese Ancestry by Location of Next of Kin and Source of Information), no. 1-15, 1944 December 16-1945 November 30 (Box 46, Folder 10)
- 3. Copies of reports, publication excerpts, research papers, and bibliographies, 1890-1945
  Materials relate to Japanese workers in the U.S., anti-Japanese attitudes, and the impact of the war on Japanese American communities.
  - United States Bureau of the Census reports, Japanese Employed Workers 14 Years Old and Over by Sex, Nativity, Major Occupation, and Industry Group, for Counties and Urban Places, 1940 (Box 46, Folder 11)
    In the states of California, Oregon and Washington
  - Editorials from The Pacific Rural Press, 1895 September-1942 September (Box 47, Folder 1)
  - Excerpts from the California Fruit Growers; and Excerpts from the Western Grower and Shipper, 1890 February- 1942 February; and 1929 December-1942 September (Box 47, Folder 2)
  - Helen E. Hennefrund, Bibliography on Japanese in American Agriculture, undated (Box 47, Folder 3)
  - Reports from the US Department of Agriculture on the Japanese in American agriculture, 1942-1945 (Box 47, Folder 4)
    Lloyd H. Fisher and Ralph L. Nielsen, The Japanese in California Agriculture. Testimony submitted to the Select Committee Investigating National Defense Migration. March 1942; Adon Poli, Japanese Farm Holders on the Pacific Coast. December 1944; Walter C. McKain, Jr., When the Japanese Return to California. December 1944; Walter C. McKain, Jr., Imperial Valley holds an 'Anti-Japs' meeting. February 1945.
  - Los Angeles County Farm Bureau Monthly, vol. XV, no. 11-12 (2 copies), and vol. XVI, no. 1, 1942 April-May, and 1942 June (Box 47, Folder 5)
  - Excerpts of various publications re the Japanese in American agriculture, undated (Box 47, Folder 6)
    Sources include House Committee on Immigration, Berkeley Gazette, Associated Farmer, and Pacific Rural Press.
  - Tamotsu Shibutani, The Initial Impact of the War on the Japanese Communities in the San Francisco Bay Region: A Preliminary Report, Berkeley, 1942 (Box 47, Folder 7)
  - Richard Nishimoto, Chapter V: "Japanese in Domestic Service", undated (Box 47, Folder 8)
  - Richard Nishimoto, Chapter VI: "Japanese in Personal Service and Urban Trade", undated (Box 47, Folder 9)
  - George Yasukochi, A Study of the Vocational Experiences of University of California Alumni of Japanese Ancestry, Berkeley; and Dorothy Sheets, Anti-Japanese Agitation in California Studied at Three Periods of Crisis, Whittier College (M.A. thesis), 1941; and 1943 (Box 47, Folder 10)
  - Chitoshi Yanaga, "Comments and Suggestions," "The Nature of Anti-Oriental Attitude," and Bibliography, undated (Box 47, Folder 11)
- 4.WRA reports, newsletters, and summary reports, 1942-1945
  Materials are those through which the War Relocation Authority (WRA) provided information about the Relocation Program.
  - WRA, instruction bulletins and memoranda to WRA staff, 1942-1943 (Box 47, Folder 12)
  - WRA, information bulletins to the evacuees, written in Japanese and in English, undated (Box 47, Folder 13)
  - WRA, Second Quarterly Report and Semi-Annual Report, 1942 July 1-September 30, 1944 January 1-June 30 (Box 47, Folder 14)
  - WRA, Colorado River Relocation Center, Family Welfare Section, The Story of the Family Welfare Section, 1942 May-1945 May (Box 47, Folder 15)
  - WRA, Community Analysis Section, reports, 1943-1945 (Box 48, Folder 1)
  - WRA, Community Analysis Section, Weekly Aummary, no.21, 25-27, & 30, 1945 May 23, June 21 & 27, July 6 & 27 (Box 48, Folder 2)
  - WRA, Information Digest, no. 44 & 46, 1943 May 15 & July 15 (Box 48, Folder 3)
  - WRA, Daily News Digest, 1944 October 26-1945 April 25 (Box 48, Folder 4)
  - WRA, Weekly Press Review, no. 19; and Great Lake Area, Newsletter, 1943 May 26; and 1944 October 31 (Box 48, Folder 5)
  - WRA, Summary Notes on Segregation Conference of W.R.A. Officials, Denver, Colorado, 1943 July 26-27 (Box 48, Folder 6)
  - 轉住計画の全貌「轉住所住民の心得」 Tenjū keikaku no zenbou: 'tenjūsho jūmin no kokoroe' [Full details about the relocation program], Washington D.C., 1943 May 5 (Box 48, Folder 7)
  - WRA, All Center Conference, Salt Lake City, Utah, 1945 February 16-22 (Box 48, Folder 8)
- 5. Camp newsletters, 1942-1945
  These publications from various assembly centers and relocation camps report on conditions of their institutions.
  - Information Concerning Tule Lake Center; and 「ツーリレツキ出発期日確定す、ラファブリッジ氏より今朝発表さる」 [Tule Lake internees to be notified of day of transfer to Tule Lake] (Box 48, Folder 10)
  - Scattered issues of the Topaz Times, [vol. I, no.1]-vol.XII, no.9, 1942 September 17-1945 August 31 (Box 48, Folder 11)
    Published by the Central Utah Relocation Project, Topaz, Utah. In English and Japanese
  - Trek, vol. 1, no.1-3, 1942 December, and 1943 February & June (Box 48, Folder 12)
    Special publication of the Reports Division, Central Utah Relocation Project, Topaz, Utah
  - Civil Liberties and Test Cases, 1944 June (Box 48, Folder 13)
    Legal Committee Report, Community Council, Topaz, Utah
  - Fighting Americans, Too! 2nd Edition; Volunteers for Victory; Reinstitution of Selective Service: summary of the policies of the selective service system, War Department and W.R.A which affect Nisei; and All Aboard, 1943 April 3; March 6; 1944 June; and Spring (Box 48, Folder 14)
    Fighting Americans, Too! published by the historical committee of the Volunteers for Victory, Topaz, Utah; Volunteers for Victory published by the Resident Council for Japanese American Civil Rights, Topaz, Utah; Reinstitution of Selective Service published by the Citizens Committee and Community Council, Central Utah Project, Topaz, Utah; and All Aboard a special publication of the Citizens Committee and Community Council, Central Utah Project, Topaz, Utah
  - scattered issues of the Tanforan Tantalizer, vol. I, no. 1, 7, 10, 12, 14, & 19, 1942 May 15, June 27, July 15 & 25, August 8, and September 8 (Box 48, Folder 15)
    Newsletter for the Tanforan Assembly Center at San Bruno, California
  - Denson Magnet, vol. I, no. 1, 1943 April (Box 48, Folder 16)
    Magazine published by the Document Section, Jerome Relocation Center, Denson, Arkansas
  - Issei, Nisei, Kibei: The U.S. has put 110, 000 people of Japanese blood in "protective custody", 1944 April (Box 48, Folder 17)
    The English version which originally appeared in the April 1944 issue of Fortune Magazine was reprinted as the Gila News-Courier Supplement (n.d.), and its Japanese translation in ten installments from April 20 to May 16, 1944 in the Gila News-Courier Japanese secton. The Gila News-Courier was the newspaper for the Gila River Relocation Center in Arizona.
  - The Pen, 1943 November 6 (Box 48, Folder 18)
    A special anniversary issue published by the Outpost, Rohwer Relocation Center, Relocation, Arkansas
  - Family Welfare Orientation Program, 1944 April 4-8 & 10-14 (Box 48, Folder 19)
    Report prepared by the Colorado River Relocation Center, Poston, Arizona
  - America in the War and America in the Peace, 1944 May 30 (Box 48, Folder 20)
    A copy of an address delivered by Ralph P. Merritt, Manzanar Relocation Center Director
  - Correspondence and documents re Charlotte B. DeForest, WRA Counselor, and adult education programs in the Manzanar Relocation Center, Manzanar, California, 1944 November-1945 July (Box 49, Folder 1)
    A couple of items written in Japanese
- 6. Correspondence of the Tajiris, 1944 April-1945 October
  Larry Tajiri was the editor of the Pacific Citizen newspaper. These correspendences mostly re the preparation of a new pamphlet by the Japanense American Citizens League (JACL) on the Japanese American war efforts.
  - Correspondence of the Tajiris (Mr. and Mrs. Larry Tajiri), 1944 April-1945 October (Box 48, Folder 9)
- 7. Copies of reports, publications, and a research paper, 1945-1947
  Materials concern the postwar resettlement of evacuees and the effect of evacuation on the Japanese community in Seattle
  - Reports, bulletins and leaflets on the postwar resettlement of evacuees, 1945-1947 (Box 49, Folder 2)
  - Documents re the Chicago Resettlers Committee, 1945-1947 (Box 49, Folder 3)
    Includes scattered issues of the Chicago Resettler, March 29, 1946-June 1947 (6 issues total), and mimeographed reports of the Committee, 1946-1947
  - S. Frank Miyamoto and Robert W. O'Brien, A Survey of Some Changes in the Seattle Japanese Community Resulting from the Evacuation, undated (Box 49, Folder 4)
    Unpublished paper
- 8. Office files of Wayne M. Collins, 1946-1955
  Wayne M. Collins (1900-1974) was a civil rights attorney with the American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU) who served as legal counsel for the Peruvian Japanese interned in the United States during World War II.
  - Chronological files containing documents, records, and correspondence on the Peruvian Japanese internees (folder 1 of 10), 1946 (Box 49, Folder 5)
  - Chronological files containing documents, records, and correspondence on the Peruvian Japanese internees (folder 2 of 10), 1947 January-June (Box 49, Folder 6)
  - Chronological files containing documents, records, and correspondence on the Peruvian Japanese internees (folder 3 of 10), 1947 July-December (Box 49, Folder 7)
  - Chronological files containing documents, records, and correspondence on the Peruvian Japanese internees (folder 4 of 10), 1948 (Box 49, Folder 8)
  - Chronological files containing documents, records, and correspondence on the Peruvian Japanese internees (folder 5 of 10), 1949 (Box 49, Folder 9)
  - Chronological files containing documents, records, and correspondence on the Peruvian Japanese internees (folder 6 of 10), 1950 (Box 49, Folder 10)
  - Chronological files containing documents, records, and correspondence on the Peruvian Japanese internees (folder 7 of 10), 1951 (Box 49, Folder 11)
  - Chronological files containing documents, records, and correspondence on the Peruvian Japanese internees (folder 8 of 10), 1952 (Box 49, Folder 12)
  - Chronological files containing documents, records, and correspondence on the Peruvian Japanese internees (folder 9 of 10), 1953 (Box 49, Folder 13)
  - Chronological files containing documents, records, and correspondence on the Peruvian Japanese internees (folder 10 of 10), 1954 (Box 49, Folder 14)
  - Records and documents relating to a test suit filed by Iwamori Sakasegawa before the US District Court, 1946 (Box 49, Folder 15)
    Iwamori Sakasegawa, along with Chika Yamasaki, was one of two Peruvian Japanese to file test suits on June 25, 1946 to prevent deportation to Japan, charging that they were kidnapped by the US Military Police.
  - Records and documents relating to a test suit filed by Chika Yamasaki before the US District Court, 1946-1953 (Box 49, Folder 16)
    Chika Yamasaki, along with Iwamori Sakasegawa, was one of two Peruvian Japanese to file test suits on June 25, 1946 to prevent deportation to Japan, charging that they were kidnapped by the US Military Police.
  - Records and documents relating to the appeals filed to the US Immigration Service on behalf of the Nakamatsu family, 1951-1954 (Box 50, Folder 1)
  - Records and documents relating to the appeals filed to the US Immigration Service on behalf of Isamu Kurotobi, 1943-1955 (Box 50, Folder 2)
  - Documents and records relating to the deportation proceedings initiated by the US Immigration Service against the Peruvian Japanese interned at the Terminal Island Immigration Station in Terminal Island, California., 1946 (Box 50, Folder 3)
  - Documents and records relating to the deportation proceedings initiated by the US Immigration Service against the Peruvian Japanese interned at the Alien Internment Camp in Crystal City, Texas., 1946 (Box 50, Folder 4)
  - Documents and records relating to the deportation proceedings initiated by the US Immigration Service against the Peruvian Japanese interned at Santa Fe Internment Camp in Santa Fe, New Mexico., 1946 (Box 50, Folder 5)
  - Personal records of 65 Peruvian Japanese and their families interned at Santa Fe, 1946 (Box 50, Folder 6)
  - Personal records of 91 Peruvian Japanese and their families interned at Crystal City, 1946 (Box 50, Folder 7)
  - Individual records on the deportation hearings by the US Immigration Service-- Aida to Dodohara, 1946 (Box 50, Folder 8)
  - Individual records on the deportation hearings by the US Immigration Service-- Fujii to Gushi, 1946 (Box 50, Folder 9)
  - Individual records on the deportation hearings by the US Immigration Service-- Hamamura to Hori, 1946 (Box 50, Folder 10)
  - Individual records on the deportation hearings by the US Immigration Service-- Ikari to Inamine, 1946 (Box 50, Folder 11)
  - Individual records on the deportation hearings by the US Immigration Service-- Kage to Kawai, 1946 (Box 50, Folder 12)
  - Individual records on the deportation hearings by the US Immigration Service-- Kihara to Kurotobi, 1946 (Box 51, Folder 1)
  - Individual records on the deportation hearings by the US Immigration Service-- Maoki to Murono, 1946 (Box 51, Folder 2)
  - Individual records on the deportation hearings by the US Immigration Service-- Naganuma to Noguni, 1946 (Box 51, Folder 3)
  - Individual records on the deportation hearings by the US Immigration Service-- Ohara to Ozaki, 1946 (Box 51, Folder 4)
  - Individual records on the deportation hearings by the US Immigration Service-- Sadamaru to Suzuki, 1946 (Box 51, Folder 5)
  - Individual records on the deportation hearings by the US Immigration Service-- Takahashi to Tsutsui, 1946 (Box 51, Folder 6)
  - Individual records on the deportation hearings by the US Immigration Service-- Uchiyama to Watanabe, 1946 (Box 51, Folder 7)
  - Individual records on the deportation hearings by the US Immigration Service-- Yakabi to Yoshizumi, 1946 (Box 51, Folder 8)